If you really want to hear my story,
then you must first become accustomed to the idea of hearing an unpleasant one.
Oh, pardon. The name: Francis.
I belong to a species which is easily overlooked by humans.
Here it is, our new home.
Come on, Francis, out you go.
Moving places is what I hate the most in life,
but Gustav, my life companion, isn’t considerate in this regard.
He’s a trained archaeologist who specializes in Egyptian gods,
but he keeps us fed by writing trash novels.
Whenever he’s out of ideas, he moves.
He believes that helps.
This is heavy! Where’s that key?
Ah, there.
Heavenly! It just needs a bit of renovation!
Come on, Francis! Or do I have to carry you over the threshold?
The musty stench hit me like a sledgehammer.
In a flash I realized that this unpleasant smell was not ascending from the basement of the building,
but creeping down from the upper floor.
It was a mixture of pharmacy, veterinary practice and toxic waste dump...
and I should never have set paw in this place.
Francis, isn’t this beautiful?
This will be great! Renovating, rehabilitating, modernizing.
Ah, yes, there’s still a lot of work to do!
Where shall I put the books?
Yes...ah, here! This is good.
And the litter box? Yes, let’s see.
Oh, this is such a nice place.
Look, Francis, we’ve got old stucco!
Ah, the porcelain, where to put it?
I’ll figure it out eventually.
Well, well...
What I saw there could be called my welcoming gift.
There he lay, a black fellow, legs stretched out.
Only he wasn’t asleep.
Can-opener!
Can-opener? What do you mean?
It was the damned can-opener. They did it!
They made little Sasha an extra ventilation hole in the neck!
You mean humans? Did you witness it?
Shit, no! But who would do this except a fucking can-opener,
good for nothing other than opening our food cans! Shit!
This is already the 4th ’cold bag’.
You mean this is already the 4th dead body?
You’re probably new here, eh?
Are you moving into that garbage dump over there? Nice spot.
I always go there to piss!
No, this wasn’t a can-opener. His neck has been shredded.
What do you call yourself, smart-ass?
Francis.
That’s all I need! Archie.
Cheers! Cheers, Archie! Isn’t this great?
Fanstastic. This atmosphere! I was fascinated from the beginning!
Really!
A doctor’s office? That would explain the chemical smell.
Don’t you think that parquet floor is a big job for just me, Archie?
But parquet is the least you can do, Gustav, it’s an absolute must!
These days, homeless people use carpet while they beg on street sides.
As young rebels we still have our golden ideals.
At least as long as you don’t own a ’superflat’.
If later on we realize we didn’t become super rebels,
what’s left for us then?
This parquet-fetishist was Archibald Philip Purpur, or Archie. A professional trendsetter, if you will.
Until next time, Archie.
He’s the only friend my poor can opener Gustav has.
Apart from me, of course.
It’s a difficult time for you Francis, I know.
But I brought your favourite music. Mahler’s ’The Resurrection Symphony’!
Sleep well.
Who are you? Where are you?
Come here, my boy.
Come here and look at this wonderful thing I have for you.
Looking for your old peeing spot? Pissing’s over for you!
This place is soon to be renovated.
Cold bag?
Devil, how... yeah. Cold bag.
Let me guess. It’s a guy, right?
Like the other 4 corpses.
Shit, yes!
How the deuce did you know?
Well, it’s just a guess.
At any rate, this time it was old Deep Purple who bit the dust.
His neck looks as if someone used it to try out his new ice pick.
One question: was Deep Purple castrated?
Purple, neutered! Man!
Purple was beyond such gay things.
He was about as old as Methuselah, but looked much older.
“Hum”, is that all you have to say?
Your silent departures are beginning to annoy me!
Where is Deep Purple’s corpse now?
Can you take me there?
Why not?
Hey! What do they call you, smart-ass?
Blaubart! But I’m happy I’ve had a few more pussies than Henry the 8th!
The longer I had to follow this proud, hardy invalid and watched his misery,
the more I wondered to what or whom he had been a victim.
Dead end!
Oh please! What have we here? The typical nasty loafers.
Oh shit, Hermann and Hermann!
Don’t tell me you want to yet again rapturously explain the advantages of being neutered.
But I believe you, yes, boys.
Without the balls and bags one carries much less weight.
Kong, why do you still hang around with these dipshits?
Blaubart, my old cripple!
I see your trips to the gay scene were very successful!
The little one behind you is indeed a fine specimen.
Is he teaching you some tricks?
No, he wants to show you personally, since he has the ideal position for you three!
I see you’re looking for a fight! Okay, you got one.
But I assume you are more interested in my friend Francis.
In this case you must know,
I won’t sit idly by in such an unfair fight!
So, how do you want it, old bastard?
I’m shitting in my pants in fear, buddy.
And as for you, sweetie,
you can bet your life on it that we’ll be having an interesting
converstation in the not-too-distant future.
One that you won’t quickly forget.
So until then, handsome ones!
Hey, Blaubart.
Yeah?
I fear you’ve betrayed your principles.
You don’t say. And why, may I ask?
Well, you told them I was your friend.
In my opinion, the last few minutes of his life happened like this:
The killer bit him several times in the neck. Outside.
This is evidenced by the traces of blood in the garden.
Purple just managed to drag himself into the garage.
Remarkable for his age.
Didn’t you tell me, Purple was beyond such gay things?
You mean sex, right?
Yes! Old Purple too was in heat when the killer caught him!
The most striking feature of this series of murders is sexuality.
The killer himself is in heat and has some unusual views on competitive behaviour in the district.
Or perhaps he has something against reproduction in general.
In my day we called it plugging!
And I’m still saying: it was a goddamn can-opener!
Shit, yes!
We shouldn’t kid ourselves.
The bloody hole is a bite.
Anyway, it looks like it’s time for me to learn more about this unfortunate area and its residents.
And you’ll help me with that, Blaubart.
Oh, will I, Mr. Inspector?
Good, tomorrow I’ll introduce you to someone.
You are not the only smart-ass in our foggy ’London for idiots.’
The sound came directly from the first floor.
I was surprised that Gustav hadn’t woken up to the noise.
Halleluja, Claudandus is at peace!
Damn irrepressible curiosity!
Obey God’s work! Deliver us!
My God, what planet had I landed on?
After only a small punishment he received great blessings
because God tested him and found him worthy!
In the name of Brother Claudandus!
In the name of Brother Claudandus,
who has sacrificed himself for us and has become God! Claudandus,
oh holy Claudandus!
Hear our pain, hear our voices, hear our prayer!
Take our sacrifice now!
Yes!
Take the sacrifice!
His end was bad luck.
His departure from us, tragic. But he is at peace!
Hallelujah! Hallelujah!
In the name of Brother Claudandus, who now dwells among the immortals!
He will judge nations and rule over nations!
Trust in him, and know the truth!
Grace and mercy his chosen will be given!
Deliver us!
Truly, this activity was beyond ’The Aristocats’.
Oh, Claudandus,
Son of the pain and light!
Our wounds are full of blood, as once your wounds were full of blood.
Recovery—
There’s someone up there!
What are you idiots waiting for?
Go, go, go, go up!
Bring him here!
Go, grab him!
Heavens!
Frankenstein’s laboratory! Or much, much worse.
What did it all mean?
Go, spread out! We need to surround him!
I can smell him.
He must be here somewhere.
He was here.
But where is he now?
You’re a new one, right?
Yes, correct.
My name is Francis.
Friend or foe?
Friend! Forever friend!
A friend who fell from the sky.
Not from the sky...
Well, through the skylight.
I’m on the run from some crazies in the Claudandus sect.
Sounds like those idiots.
Has daybreak begun yet?
Surely you can see—
You’re blind!
I am not blind.
I just cannot see.
Do you ever go outside?
No, but still...
Not a single day has passed where I would not have liked to see this wicked world once.
I’m sorry.
Why?
There are worse things in life.
One does endure quite a bit...
Except perhaps having to stay in a dog kennel.
Were you always like this?
I mean like...
... so blind?
Yes.
From birth.
But it is strange, I see pictures.
Pictures in my head.
What kind of pictures?
I see many people gathered around me.
They are so big and bright.
One of the men leans over and smiles at me.
He suddenly has something shiny in his hand, and it hurts me.
And I fall asleep.
You were not blind from birth.
Some human has done something terrible to you.
Shall I tell you something?
Those creatures are the nicest kind.
Who else would keep such a blind hen as me?
May I ask you an unusual question?
Erm...
Felicitas.
During the last few weeks, at night, did you hear anything unusual, ehm..
You mean the death screams?
Heavens, you’re the first witness I have met!
Why are you so interested?
Well, it is about murder, after all.
Murder? Sounds pretty dramatic.
I think it is merely heightened rivalries.
How do you come to that conclusion?
The death cries.
All of them came from males who were on the road, tempted by some ’Madonna’.
Suddenly they are joined by someone who they seem to know very well.
Did this person speak to the victims?
Yes. Although, I did not understand him.
But his tone of voice was so keen...  pregnant with meaning.
As though he were trying to convince the other of something.
And later?
After that was the death cry.
What do you know about this Claudandus sect?
All I know is that they worship a martyr called Claudandus,
who allegedly lived here in the infirmary decades ago; tormented by humans—even tortured.
Tortured...
Why did you leave? We just wanted to chat with you.
With 360 volts loosening my tongue, eh?
Felicitas.
I’ll be back.
For now, I need to discuss something with that guy up there!
On one hand you came to me so I’d do something about these murders,
on the other hand you kept quiet about the big picture, Blaubart.
Excuse me?
I’m just passing the time! This whole Claudandus thing is just entertainment.
No biggie.
No biggie?!
It has existed for some years.
Joker was the first one to distribute the teaching of Claudandus.
Over the years he has found more and more supporters.
Joker?
The aged master of ceremonies with the shrunken head charm, right?
Yes. But the thing really is harmless, Francis.
Nobody knows who Claudandus really was.
Perhaps he never existed.
May I?
Yes, yes, go ahead, eat.
And then take me to that genius you told me about.
For a can-opener this cooking is really first class!
I checked the encyclopedia.
Claudandus is Latin, and means ’One who should or must be sealed.’
There must be more to it.
I can’t imagine.
You think?!
I think non-stop. You’re surprised!
Well, I also read a book once.
Blaubart was here!
Very impressive.
Are we in the house of an art professor or... a pimp?
Shit, I don’t exactly know.
I think the man who owns this bin
does something with science or parapsychology.
Devil knows.
Welcome, dear friends!
I was wondering what took you so long.
Blaubart told me—
Well, this smart-a—
This guy here is Francis,
and the weisenheimer over there is called Pascal.
Francis? Francis.
It is a pleasure and an honor to meet you, Francis.
May I offer you both a bite to eat?
Thank you, but we just ate.
Well, personally, I don’t have anything against a few appetizers.
Go ahead, you know your way to the kitchen.
Frankly, I wouldn’t once have dreamed that even one of us could use a computer.
This is simply a humble attempt to discover the cruel butcher in our area with the help of the computer.
Do you know the meaning of this word?
Felidae?
As far as I know it’s the scientific term for our type of feline.
Felidae.
Evolution brought an amazing variety of organisms to life.
But none compel a greater respect and admiration than the Felidae.
What’s included in your list, Pascal?
All the inhabitants of our territory.
Name, age, gender, race, etc.
That reminds me... I have yet to register you.
Interesting.
Isn’t it?
Especially if it can help solve this murder case.
Did you know that all victims at the time of—
Yes.
They all were chasing after some females in heat.
Ehm, I have an idea.
Yes?
Command the computer to single out the races of the victims.
Hats off.
None of the five were noble exemplars of Felidae.
Odd. All the victims were male, in heat and European Shorthair.
Wrong.
Not all. I have yet to register the 6th victim yet.
Wha-what 6th victim?
Felicitas?
Yes.
Unfortunately, Felicitas too.
No, Pascal! That’s impossible!
I was talking with her only an hour ago!
However, I was informed of it just before you and Blaubart arrived.
...and the way her eyes were wide open.
As if, even durion her moment of death, she desired nothing more than to see.
Life goes on, Francis.
Where did you get that nonsense from?
From the one book you read?
Just saying.
Whoever has Felicitas on his conscience will have to pay for it.
Do you hear me, neck-biter? You are going to pay for this!
We’ll get you, shit-head!
No matter what Pascal says: Felicitas had to die because she was a witness.
All this time we have been tailed.
This is not a frantic madman. He sticks cold-heartedly to his calculated plan.
Francis!
The riddle’s solution is quite simple.
Felidae!
Evolution brought an amazing variety of organisms to life.
But none compel a greater respect and admiration than the Felidae!
Do not forget that case of Claudandus.
He is the key!
And hop,
hop, hop!
And hop, hop, hop!
Experiments on plant hybrids! Experiments on plant hybrids!
Experiments on plant hybrids!
Hey, you? Did you sleep well?
One would have to be a cat. Eat...
sleep...
eat, sleep, yes...
Great thinkers have their little hobbies to clear their mind.
I did what I always do when I need to clear my head and relive some stress.
Rat hunting.
There they were, yes! Always busy!
Always funny! Always sociable!
Patiently waiting for the big day when they’ll achieve world domination.
The laboratory is a dream.
Pharmarox has spared no expense.
My assistants are Ziebold and Grey.
I know that my fibrin glue will revolutionize medicine.
The first attempt failed.
Instead of sticking, the mixture has completely corroded the flesh.
I have to concentrate on the reduction of maleic acid.
It simply defies logic.
Just this morning this handsome lad ran up to me.
We decided to make him our mascot.
I’ll start a new attempt.
I fear that the nameless stray will have to kick the bucket.
A miracle has happened.
It worked right away!
Most likely, the young stray proved...
invaluable to science.
He will be commemorated as Claudandus.
In history bo—
We had to take apart Claudandus again.
There is some factor in his gene structure
that allows his body to easily absorb the mixture.
He is a... mutation.
They have cut our fundings.
But I am Professor Preterius!
Test subject deficiency? No problem.
Yes, off you go, colleague Ziebold!
Sacrifices! Science requires sacrifices!
Thanks to my sophisticated breeding program,
some of the females have ensured supply.
Are you still able to produce offspring, Claudandus?
I imagine an entirely new,
totally unique cat breed!
A super-race!
Yes, Claudandus speaks to me!
Fascinating, is it not?
Absolutely no humor in the animal.
Didn’t he ask me to let him out of the cage?
And duel him?
What’s that? I must... Claudan—!
Didn’t I promise that we’d have a conversation face-to-face?
What is it you wanted to talk about?
Is it about the stealth stalking?
This is really funny.
Kong!? Don’t you think we should turn to more serious matters?
Yes, you’ve got it, brother.
A monster lurks this area.
Won’t you help me to look for this lunatic?
You don’t have to look for him anymore.
You?
And why do you kill?
Why, you ask?
Because all those guys risked a fat lip.
You’re a huge bastard, but your motive isn’t convincing.
You’ll soon realize how convincing I am.
Is that fair?
No!
Just leave him to me!
No, not that!
Shorty is out of breath.
He probably sucked too much shoddy dry food.
Yes, I’m out of breath.
But it looks like I’m not the only one.
What are you blabbering about?
Solitaire!
Oh, Solitaire! What have they done to you?
My God, what have they done to you?
My poor, poor Solitaire!
Who was she?
Solitare was the boss’ favourite chick.
And what was in her was probably from him.
I’ll kill him! I’ll make mincemeat out of him!
I’ll rip off his balls and stuff them into his mouth!
I, I...
What heartless creature was it?
Who? Who? Damn it!
You...it can’t have been you. There wasn’t enough time.
But then who? Who was?
Say your prayers!
You rascal!
Any idea where the waddler went, smart-ass?
With this horrible weather I don’t even know where my home is.
He probably fled even farther, boss. There are only 3 gardens left.
We’ll snatch him.
Yes, yes.
Yes! Come on!
I’ve had enough of this nightmare.
The murder of Kong’s beloved Solitaire destroyed all my theories about the murders in one stroke.
And now I am stuck who knows how deep in this hell hole!
I was wondering what was taking you so long.
Shit, I’m too old for slides!
Hush! Not so loud.
Not so loud!
I heard Kong whine like a muezzin in delirium,
saw the poor Solitaire and followed you over the walls.
Where are we now?
No idea.
Catacombs.
Not so loud.
Oh, shit! A mass grave!
A fucking—
Do you smell that?
Yes.
Disgusting!
The stench of decay. Kong was right.
The waddler is the killer.
But I see neither Sasha nor Deep Purple, or Fe—
Don’t harm the deadwatcher.
Certainly, the deadwatcher has broken the sacred rule.
For that he’ll have to suffer bitterly.
Do you always have early Mass before going for someone’s neck?
What is your name, my friend?
They call me Jesaja.
Are you responsible for all of these?
I mean all these skeletons,
did you kill them and then transport them here?
Oh no, stranger.
The dead come to me.
They are sent by the Prophet.
If you ask me he’s a regular nutcase.
Where did you come from, Jesaja?
And how on earth did you stumble upon this terrible place?
Once there was the dreamland where I was born.
In dreamland the Prophet wielded power, who’d finally bring us salvation.
God heard the prayers of the Prophet,
and when the day exploded into light,
so, too, the dreamland did explode.
And the tormented aimlessly fled in all directions.
What happened to the Prophet?
He went to heaven.
Padre Joker told me so.
Joker?
The leader of the Claudandus sect?
Since the dawn of time, he has called this temple his home.
He carried me here and cared for me henceforth.
But then he left me...
to spread the word of the Prophet.
And how did Padre Joker explain this pretty bone collection?
Oh, no. When Padre Joker and I lived here together,
the dead were not among us.
However, one day, after Father Joker had left,
I heard rumbling in one of the tunnels.
When I arrived at the exit hole,
I saw a dead sister come flying down.
And suddenly I heard the voice of the Lord.
And what did he say?
That I as chosen to fulfill the service of the deadwatcher.
But now everything has changed.
Neither does the Prophet speak to me lately,
nor does he send dead ones to the other realm.
He has forgotten about me.
So you were out last night looking for dead ones yourself, correct?
Did you notice anything special about the dead? I mean,
were there, for example, excited ones amoung them?
So it was, Brother.
But some strangely disfigured came down to the temple as well.
And pregnant?
Many.
Ah! So many, brother.
Cod natural.
Cod cooked.
Cod lightly fr-fried.
Cod in mayonnaise... Cod!
Cod, Cod.. Do you even understand what we have just learned?
Mayonnaise.
There weren’t 7 murder victims but hundreds.
This series of murders dates back many years.
Probably back to the closure of the laboratory.
So, so.
Earlier in the mortuary temple you asked a very clever question.
Namely?
Why the bodies of Sasha, Deep Purple, Solitaire and...
Felicitas weren’t in the temple.
Maybe he is like me, the murderer!
For I, too, slowly loose my fancy! I’m hungry!
I’m tired and I long for co—
I’m hungry, I’m tired, I yearn for cod! Cod, my God!
The old Joker is the only one who knows something about the Prophet Claudandus.
Ironically, the guy who operates this electroshock-cult.
Wh-what did you say back then: it’s a time-filler, a thrill?
Something like that.
Sometimes it seems to me that this sect-circus serves a particular purpose.
As if it was a preparation for something very special, inconceivable!
Such as.. cod?
I have found you at last!
Of course, my dear Francis.
I am the Prophet. I am the human and the animal,
and I am Felidae.
Come with us, Francis.
Everything that once was and all that will be has lost its meaning, Francis.
Come with us.
Come with us!
You can find something better than death everywhere!
Come with us on the long, wonderful journey.
And what will we find there?
Everything that we have lost, Francis.
Francis!
Who are you?
What breed do you belong to?
Breed! What an antique and isolated term.
I don’t belong to a race.
Your mistress is, well, the way she is.
You mean your race is new?
Not new, but old.
Or, rather, old and new and different!
Make a rhyme out of it yourself, Francis.
How do you know my name?
A little bird told me.
And what’s your name?
My name wouldn’t mean much to you.
But don’t worry about it.
It’ll all come out in the wash
and all will end well. Trust me.
Do I know the girl at least?
I hope you know her.
She can help us get a little bit closer to solving the puzzle.
Case? Solution?
Don’t tell me you’re still interested?
Judging by your unbearable stench, you “reduplicated” all day long...
Oh! My God!
Yes, yes, you’re right, old friend.
To work. First, where is Joker this very moment?
He’s probably home alone, preparing for his next Bible lesson.
Where is his home?
Quite a way from the territory.
His can opener runs a shop for porcelain and valuable glass.
Good. I’m going to pay Pascal a visit.
In the meantime, you’ll march to Joker and tell him that Pascal and I wish to speak with him about the murders.
Do you really think the old Joker is the killer?
Don’t forget what we learned from Jesaja.
Joker is deeply - and I mean very deeply involved with it.
The question is if I can expose him.
Ah, right, before I forget...
I erm..
This morning, I made acquaintance with a lady,
whose, um, race is completely alien to me. Sandy colour with glowing yellow eyes.
I know the mix.
Are there many of them?
Shit, yes! It’s probably some breeding particularly high in the market.
The whole territory is full of those orotund braggadocios.
But with this breed the can openers pissed down their own legs.
What do you mean?
They aren’t like us!
Well, somehow I get the impression that during the whole damn breeding process, domestication fell completely by the wayside.
These new ones, they are wilder, more dismissive, even more dangerous.
Like.. predators?
Yes.
My compliments.
I’ve lived in this district for years, Francis, and I did not even notice a fraction of the horrible things you have found out in such a short time.
Hats off!
Have you saved information on fellows who suddenly, for whatever reason, left district?
Of course.
With this list, can we check how many disappeared for no apparent reason and when each one did so?
Uhum
What’s your guess as to why the murderer no longer entrusted his last seven victims to the deadwatcher Jesaja?
That is an important point, Francis.
Because it is an indicator that our friend has begun to make mistakes.
I can hardly believe that such a prodigy or horror would make even a single mistake!
Maybe he wants to point us to something?
That’s good!
No it’s not. Because we don’t have the slightest clue what he wants us to know.
To himself and his acts!
As if!
The average IQ of the territory’s residents is so shamefully low that
there’s no one capable of understanding his subtle signs.
Well, and if uhm..
What if he only wants to draw someone very specific to his life’s work?
That’s a good one!
Why?
Because you speak of a life’s work for the very first time, Francis!
Don’t you get it?
He deliberately aims to be seen through!
The whole guy is strange.
He’s like a riddle. No,
He is the riddle and is only waiting for the one who will solve it.
Joker’s either had to leave in a hurry or he’s having stomach trouble.
Joker. For me, one of the prime suspects.
Could be right.
He saw the drama regarding Preterius’ laboratory, saw the opportunity
to create a Martyr-Religion that resolves around Claudandus’ sufferings.
That is possible.
Tell me a bit more about the lady you made acquaintance with this morning.
Well, she was not like the others.
Professor Preterius’ killer breed?
Why not?
Unlikely.
You forgot about evolution.
A new breed can also arise by chance.
Well, well. Is that so?!
So, you think my wild lady and her kind are the product of natural selection?
You are right as always, Pascal.
Don’t be so modest, Francis.
You are the true smart-ass.
May I possibly contribute something too?
Where’s Joker?
Not there. Disappeared.
What do you mean disappeared?
Dis-disappeared means disappeared!
Would you like to have a snack before you finish your report?
Old Ziebold prepared fresh liver.
Fresh liv—
Get to the point, Blaubart!
A horror house is where Joker lives!
I combed it from bottom-up and top-down but found nothing.
Joker has been murdered!
No, vanished!
He knew you were close to catching him and fled.
No, no! I refuse to accept such a cheap solution!
Calm down.
Starting tomorrow we’ll begin working seriously and draw up a list of possible survivors from Professor Preterius’s laboratory.
Watch your back, smart-ass.
What do you mean?
The neck-biter will want to get nasty revenge on the one who messed up his tour. Shit yeah.
Pascal is in danger too.
He, too, knows too much.
Based on what you’ve found out,
the killer only attacks those who are seeking sexual education.
But good old Pascal is neutered.
And moreover...well,
he doesn’t have long to live anyway.
Why not?
He has cancer. Colon cancer, I think.
The doctor only gave him a little longer than half a year.
Dear friends!
We thank you that so many of you accepted our invitation.
Well, hopefully we get to hear something!
Otherwise, someone will have to pay big time for the film I’m missing on TV!
Kong, you stupid rhinoceros!
If you even a single spark of decency, you’d at least act like you’re mourning for your Solitaire!
I’ll get that neck-biter sooner or later anyway.
You won’t catch anyone, you fool!
Do you think the guy will come knocking on your door one day to ask for forgiveness?
You sure know how to take a joke.
Kong!
The problem is that our homicidal friend has no sense of humor!
Francis and I were sitting at the computer.
We can now assume with certainty
that the murderer has killed not seven of us,
but, believe it or not,
has 450 on his conscience.
These kill—
These killings
are likely in connection with the gruesome secrets of Professors Preterius’ laboratory.
Crimes, who some of you fell victim to but do not remember today.
That’s enough!
What did you think is the reason why some of us stagger through life like total retards?
Calm down and let the wise guy continue!
Perhaps he will present us the murderer.
Unfortunately, I cannot currently present the murderer but perhaps a glimpse of the truth.
A number of you, dear friends, pay homage to the dead Claudandus, who,
as you all now know, was stuck in Professor Preterius’s laboratory, endured the worst tortu—
He did not die!
What do you know about him?
Why do you think he did not die back then?
Well, because great grandfather told me about it.
And who is your great grandfather?
Padre Joker.
He told me that in the end Claudandus fought the monster and killed it.
Dear friends!
The only one who knows what Claudandus looked like and could lead us to him is Joker.
However, Joker is de—
Disappeared! And if you ask me,
Joker adopted the identity of the Prophet.
Claudandus is dead.
No one could have survived this torture.
But Joker is alive and has fled!
Thanks to our brother Francis, his evil plans were thwarted.
Bravo! Bravo!
I already told you, I searched Joker’s place from bottom to top!
Exactly! From bottom to top!
Huh?
You had no chance to take a peek at the shelf tops!
And what now?
Well, then it must be done the hard way!
My God! It had been an execution.
And Joker must’ve agreed to it!
But what was at stake that was so incredibly important
that Joker had sacrificed himself for?
Claudandus! He had survived.
Now that Joker is dead, we have lost our prime suspect.
Right. The whole thing is as puzzling as Egyptian hieroglyphics.
Blaubart, I just had a crazy idea!
Crazy! A term that could often describe your state of mind!
Genetics.
The genetics!
The law of inheritance was first discovered by the Jesuit father Gregor Johann Mendel.
We’re being bred back!
We’re being what?
Why am I an idiot for never asking which female the murder victims were chasing?
I should’ve listened to my dreams from the very beginning.
My first nightmare...
The man without a face, that must have been, of course, Preterius!
Ear-witness Felicitas’s key words...
Although, I did not understand him.
But his tone of voice
was so keen...
Pregnant with meaning.
As though he were trying to convince the other of something.
The suspect isn’t a lunatic running amok!
He wanted to persuade the poor victims not to copulate with my hot terrace-lady or one of her fellows!
For, what did she about herself say again? "We are not new, but old"!
You mean the new ones in the territory, the super-breed?
Exactly!
There! Take a Look!
What? Is that her?
No! She is the motive.
We’re being bred back to our original form.
Back to the wild, proud felidae.
G. J. Mendel, heredity. Major work: Experiments on plant hybrids—
Experiments on plant hybrids!
Who worships Gregor Johann Mendel and has his portrait in his study?
Who assisted Preterius in his laboratory?
Well, who?
Ziebold!
Who the hell is Ziebo—?
Fresh liver!
Does that ring a bell?
Fresh liver, fresh liver... let me think.
No time to think. Come on!
Okay, you take this entrance.
I’ll climb the tree and enter the study above.
Blaubart was here.
The password, dammit!
Come on, come on, think. Think!
The damn password!
Number 287: Paschal
1986, June 18th at about 0:30am:
attempted to copulate with Trabian.
All persuasion was in vain.
Suddenly I understood!
He had to ensure that the chosen females for breeding
would pair up with corresponding male!
And if a different animal was to butt in,
well, then—
Do you know everything now, dear Francis?
Yes, Claudandus! There are only a few gaps in my knowledge!
Perhaps you’re willing to fill them?!
I’ll tell you a story of humans and animals.
A.. true story.
Yes, I am Claudandus.
I was in that lab! I have endured that agony!
When Preterius finally snapped I spoke to him!
You spoke to him?!
Yes! And he let me out of the cage.
And I put my fangs deep into his throat.
Afterwards Ziebold found me. Through him I learned Mendel’s genetics,
and suddenly I knew I could turn the wheels of history back again!
The only one who helped me was Joker.
He took care of spreading the ideology,
and I was responsible for the scientific side of the project.
After the first breeding successes the program was expanded quickly.
I had to kill, Francis, I had to!
To preserve the pureness of the breed, my pristine Felidae.
I will die soon.
Therefore I lured you on my track, for you to become my successor.
The leader of this wonderful, powerful Felidae!
And why did Joker have to bite the dust?
I wasn’t left with any other choice. He would have spilled the beans under all that pressure.
Now I really know everything.
But I wish I’d have never known!
Oh no, Francis.
You lived your ordinary little day,
and at night, you slept your carefree, ordinary little sleep
filled with peaceful, stupid dreams.
And I...
have brought you nightmares.
Didn’t I?
This world is hell, Francis!
And the culmination of all this ugliness in the universe is the human race!
I tell you, my friend, we aren’t cut from a different cloth.
You are the true human!
You think like them, you act like them!
Tell me what role you had in mind for the other species?
None.
They are stupid and victims of their fate.
But there are good people, too! Pascal, or Claudandus, or Felidae, or whoever you may be...
No! No! No! There aren’t any good humans!
They are all the same!
Animals are good creatures,
humans are evil animals!
I will fight you however I can!
And I’ll start with the erasure of this unutterable program! I’m Sorry.
You don’t have the slightest idea how sorry I am about this, Francis.
So much darkness in the world... Francis.
So much darkness.
I became evil, Francis...
but...
once as well, I was ...
good.
Blaubart!
He lost his innocence...
Blaubart...
Just like humans.
Even murderers die,
and with them the mysterious stories that, for a while, kept us on tenterhooks.
And so, that’s a farewell from your humble little Francis
and a heartfelt salute to all the smart-asses in the world.
Don’t give up hope, believing in a world,
in which animals and humans can live together in harmony.
Also, of course, smarter types than the latter.
For example: Felidae!