and we tried to,
integrate human characteristics into these cat designs.
We got the whole sortiment of
the bad guy, the buddy, the hero...
We had to develop all of these things in the process of making. And that was a big challenge, because it turned out rather fast that this movie was becoming more complex than we had imagined. Like it happens all the time.
And that was the special task with this movie to be compared with live action movies too.
Yes, that probably was one of the main challenges of my duty, to realize this demanding job in any form at all.
It even happened that drawers from all over the world showed big interest to join in, even for our bad ratings on the international market. In the end we had teams from Vancouver, Toronto, Dublin - the animation, London, Amsterdam, Hamburg as our homeplace and even from Seoul.
And the coordination ... the technical one for once, but also all these people had their own opinion, depending on from where they came from about how everything had to look like.
And do merge those parts, it seems we succeeded, but it was heavy in dispute.
Even the movie is gloomy, the production wasn't free from stress neither. One has to admit that. With the little time and the usual local budgets, our international partners sure weren't used to it.
They weren't used to it and we had to complete this project somehow.
A little anecdote [on the margin?], I just remember:
I recall this movie being completed really tight just before the premiere. I remember the Boy George song from the topic. I think I can remember that the tape was flown in by personal  messenger from London to Munich
Directly out of the studio and it could not be inserted earlier. So, it was sewn in great hurry, because we underestimated the costs of our work, because we never worked like this before.
We are now seeing the first dream sequence, one of the very special features of this movie,
to have several dream sequences throughout the movie and each... we planned to implement a different graphical solution into each one, just because we enjoyed playing with those completely new options.
And it was visually, because that was the great deal for certain animators and drawers, which could do things they weren't allowed to in other places.
Those principally where just small short movies by themselves which... to animate such scenes, animators aren't allowed to do such things usually. That's actually very rare.
Usually on the cartoon market - especially when talking about cat movies - you'd rather think about Aristocats, about nice cats, about cute animals and this is movie shows the abyss like you can see right here.
At the very latest, you now realize this isn't a children movie. And thos dream sequences are spread through the movie. There will be other scenes which were the highlights, a challenge to our work.
The drawer of the dream just now - it wasn't just one, but I remember cleatly that - about deals, Michael, one of the drawers could no longer stand the room falling apart after he had drawn him falling down board by board. He had assistants that helped him, but it was an extraordinatory task to do the the line work, the normal stuff. You have to see that. And this movie brought so many challenges to the studio, to the crew so that everyone was pulling into the same direction in spite of the overload. It's a contradiction, with cartoon, but it seems that the greater the challenge the more engagement will the people show.
Well, yes, but that's principally true throughout the life. I want to say, one needs some challenges or it'll become boring. And we were allowed to do those [sequences?]. And it was something very special that we succeeded by this very story.
And I think, by the way... the whole look of the movie looks very more expensive than the movie's budget. We had a lot of people working for minimalists honorars for what they would not have done for a normal movie, to say a children movie for sure. So we had the chance to say, okay, there's certain things, we want to take part in that, for example we had the special pleasure, the movie music if you pay attention to it, comes from <<Berkley>> which is also know as <<Adorf Meus>>, a band I like and which was in at that time [regardless of that, I never heard of anything similar to those names, sorry]. They would not have done this for a regular budget.
The people who helped out... I want to explain the mixture of the movie. If you see the houses and the designs of those backyars, the interior space too, then this basically comes from Dreakworks, because some former employees of Dreamworks were too bored to produce funny children movies and they produced a large amount of the board and layout design out of Tprpmtp - that's the linework of the backgrounds. We had to merge those with the characters coming from <<Blues>> [TODO] that's Irish professionals who seeked new chances after the ruin of <<Blues>> and helped us out and the color mix, all of the atmosphere coming up, that's from Hamburg. It was to show the German seriousnessness in the weather. That's something we're best at.
Well yes, it's a movie out of Hamburg by the weather. It's very rainy which is difficult to show in cartoon. Especially with the way we produced it back then. Rain is a special effect animation that hat to be included in the camera takes. With several expositions and had to be reflected in the animation. Effects were much more difficult to produce at that time, because you could not correct things afterwards. You had to look at the final result and if you notice the rain being too heavy or soft or the expisition wasn't right, you had to repeat all steps. That was much more costly... but then again... personally... I enjoyed working that way much more, because it was a task to do seriously.
True, I forgot about the effects, they're from London. That's John Cousen with a very very big crew, that's people who had been working for Dick Williams before who sadly lost his ... to ... Disney if I remember correctly and Disney hesitates to release it. They should do so. [Sorry, I didn't manage to hear out or find out otherwise what he's saying here, maybe a movie title]
They used to scold us because their standards of five double-expositions [tech term?] and so on. We didn't know what they're talking about and didn't reach their standards. Then we struggled and our camera team ... you can be proud of the result. It was a big challenge to heave ourselves at that niveau. What were our projects before that? The "Little Punker" and the "Ottifants"...
"Ottifants, the TV series", "the little Punker" as motion picture and "Werner", "Werner Beinhart", the first Werner movie. That means we have gained a little experience, we already had s little experience with motion pictures, about how to start such things, but everything with considerately less effort, because we had to try to imitate reality here. That's especially hard with cartoon. It's easier to just animate. Cartooney characters with special features, but here we produced something that compares to real movement. If you miss by a nuance, then everything looks annoying and bad and that was surely one of the big difficulties.
The anecdote... I talked to a former collegue 2 years ago in Trave who worked on animation and when I came up with Felidae he only said "THEM!". He always was of the opinion that they'd move more smoothely. Those directional disputes about how a real cat moves, they weren't that easy to solve. I remember our collegues in Ireland, they had real cats in their movie studio, to be well-informed. You could smell the cat pee at the meetings. But we had to live with that, we didn't have any allergic person on the staff and and it was a huge challenge to make them cats act human while not destroying the cat image, the smoothness and naturalement.
Here with these group scenes, one had to ... we couldn't make each one move on its own, so they got commando, they are to wag a little, that's it. But that's the limit with our budget. But then they are fried even better. That was fun again, with the special effects. Those are the cat haters' scenes. That torture stuff, you don't have that with Disney neither.
That's been the splatter movie of the cartoon industry.
We've been complaing all the time about our difficulties... haven't there been more fun things? Oh yes, that was a great thing too: The story originally isn't made for a cartoon movie, it's been very complex. We began to work, then it already started full scale, with a script that'd suggest a two-hours movie at least. The story is of theoretical nature, draws a difficult plot and we have tried a lot to cut back, but the cuts - it's very heavy on the word - made the movie appear very racy. We couldn't allow it to slow down or we wouldn't have been able to tell the story. And we wanted to produce a bit of paranoia too, even for the audience.
The problem was: We had way too much text and we also had no experience where to cut back and the author refused to even remove a single syllable. We had to fight for that. We just did that eventually. He didn't seem to have noticed. Akif may excuse us, but it was really a problem that we had too much text and very much action to stuff into 80 minutes.
Why 80 minutes? Of course every minute we have to animate additionally a question of our budget. And also by my opinion, a cartoon movie by the attention, just because we have an artificial reality, we lack the natural movements, those from branches or air and wind, those are missing and the audience will be tired more soon...
Here again we tried some 3D things that we put on film in antiquated ways. It was an unimaginable task, this here this tube, those few seconds. We just wanted to try it. That was back in 1993 or 1994, really a premiere. And we wanted to include it in a way that nobody notices that it actually looks completely different and we could afford it and gained a lot of experience by it.
The other 3D effects principally are all... those are layout effects, that means we used certain tricks with the layout in the way the camera moves or the drawing changes perspective during the panning. Those things were introduced to us by a befriended drawer, Armin McCunian, an armenian coeval who lived in Canada, who was a top layouter and who gained us a lot of know-how for the company that shaped/coined for the last 8 years. That experience, it was great to be allowed to work on such things.
This mass scene too was very costly at that time. If you look at it, we just wanted to create big pictures to go along with the story and to fit the expectations and if there's more than one character in the picture to completely animate, then it became a lot more material and work.
This is funny too. This is also by Armin and his crew in Toronto. This is in fact an English living room, but the difference to a German living room... I could explain quickly what the difference was... and that's why we have this anglo style, nobody would notice today.
This anglo style fits the atmosphere of the story, as to where the movie plays, in Germany or somewhere else isn't important, but it has a certain English touch, that's what we've settled down onto. We have photographed the location in Bonn at that time, we've found it there. Together with the author who had a certain image in mind. He lived in Bonn at that time and had written the novell there and said "Yes, this is exactly the backyard I had in mind when I was writing". Then we sat down with photos and designs and stuff to get the atmosphere, too. Then we had to decide where the story plays, at what weather, with what an atmosphere. Of course.. a sun bathing Spain at the coast... it wouldn't fit the story.
But then we were at the right place for the atmosphere at our studio in Hamburg.
A danish weekend cottage wouldn't do it neither.
Neither. I agree.
One characteristic of this movie was the cast of actually top-quality speakrs. It was a pleasure for us too to work with Mario Adorf. We knew Ulrich Tukur from earlier productions. Something ony few people know, he has spoken in the first Werner movie, too, because he was a friend from Hamburg. Meanwhile he settled in Venice. It was just a chance, because the producer attached importance to selling the movie by the names too. That opened up the chance for us to make recordings with them. With Brandauer as well, who did his recordings for the role in 2 days. I especially remember Mario Adorf as an especially professional and sympathical person.
The voices were, especially with those longthy dialogs, the only chance to bring a little expression into the characters. The voices for cartoons are done first in fact. If they don't point into any direction, then the animators are lost, because then attitude and mimics, the mood of the expression doesn't come clear.
Cartoons just aren't done at a single set of a big team, but spread all over. Then you have to be geared to the concrete. If the voice is strong, then you'll get a good animation too
Yes, the voices principally are a directional declaration for the drawer who has to realize it and the voices make up the mood the timing... all of that. That's why we dod the voice recordings first. We really have a radio play which has to be cut down to the length. We have this radio play and we have to work with the speakers so that they can blindly feel into the story and into the atmosphere and then can express that with their voices.
It's really a nice, convenient task, because by this you also learn the structure of the movie and what the atmosphere feels like.
One of the few funny scene. We were craving for those after a while, because the movie is very very serious, dark and mysterious. We weren't used to that kind of work and that setting in the kitchen sink, it was fun and brought back the old smile, but there wasn't much to smile with this movie and that's probably surprised the audience, too
It's very unusual. And I haven't ever seen such a gloomy cartoon again.
No, that's probably the last one.
The first and last one.
The first ones will be the last ones, right.
Yes, another funny scene. The "little Punker" still was full of those feces. This time we were only allowed twice, I think.
Now it's getting theoretical. That's very unusual too for a cartoon to start to philosophize that far. All that stuff about races and genes. First of all that's unusual for cats and then even more for cartoons.
Here we had to find a way to mediate the rather complex story in a reduced and understandable way. That sure is easier in the book, because there you have all time in the world to explain a complex fact. But here we had to make everything graspable in a short time, that was - principally with every movie difficult - but in this case it was especially difficult, because of our limited time and the story requiring much more time. And we had to work atmospherical too, because the atmosphere is especially important to get people into mood. So that one gets the feeling what this movie is about. So if we used - let's say - "weaker imagery" for the movie, it'd be a rather weakly imagened radio play. So we needed strong imagery to be aedequat. [imagery? the art of explaining things by images]
And yes, action, once in a while, so you don't become deaf from all those dialogs. Of course all the story works by the text, it's heavy on word. That's Pirinçi in his book too - long monologs, huge sentences, that's naturally not easy to realize. It's still full of it, this movie. One surely can watch it over and over and will find something new again.
Good Evening, my Name is Michael Schaak, I want to introduce myself, I'm the director of this movie.
And I have to ponder what happened back then, because ...
it has been 8 years until today since when we produced this movie and...
we will try to tell you some of the anecdotes which we still remember.
We - that means: Me too. My name is Veit Vollmer.. I am assistent director of this movie and have led the directions together with Michael.
As you can see here, one of the first 3D cars of movie history. We worked it out on the computer, printed and painted it, then put it under the camera.
Well, this is where you can recognize that this movie still has been made the traditional way, with movie camera, the film was colored with Placker colors [dunno Placker, maybe a kind of colors used for films]
It has been produced traditionally all the way. Meanwhile this changed:
Today we only work on this stuff by using computers. There's no film anymore, there's no more movie cameras.
Meanwhile those things have become history.
And by that it didn't become easier.
Especially with this movie... we have just seen the villa from the outside, now we will see it from the inside, we had exciting high expectations.
The villa which we are entering has been taken from a street in Bonn.
So we had to fly in our Canadian designer so they can draw a villa. That is to say the exact villa of the author in Bonn and and copy it into the trick movie.
It has been foundation of the novel so it had to be authentic.
As we said another piece ofhistory - Bonn, the old capital [of Germany]. That's gone, too.
What we wanted to add ...
this movie is a trick movie which never has been done like this in Europe before.
and regrettably I think there won't be another one ...
that is to say, we made a trick movie which isn't directed at a children audience,
but we have put a novell on film which is a thriller and which is directed at an adult audience.
It was a chance. We got the offer to do this movie
and it was a great challenge, because many of the drawers we knew back from
several productions like "Werner" and "der kleene Punker"
wanted to do something visually ambitious
and then we... we got the chance,
to do something where we could show off our skills
and what was a lot of fun for us as producers of this movie...
not another "Aristocats", but a movie which...
which we turned into a thriller and... yes, a dark movie somehow.
Here goes the first corpse,
I don't think this were possible in a Disney movie.
The challenge of this movie was the book of Akif Pirinçi playing in a cats' world.
Because of that it would not have been possible to...
yes, it just would not have been possible to realize the movie in a real world.
That means with speaking cats, that's why the producer got the idea:
That is a topic for cartoon.
And that is where we came into play.
We so to speak have a radio play.
Which has to be cut to the right length.
We have this radio play and have to work with the speakers so that they can feel into the story and express the atmosphere with their voice.
It is a really fun and enjoyable task, because after this you know the structure of the movie and its atmosphere.
One of the few funny scenes.
After some time we craved for those scenes, because the story is really really serious and dark and mysterious.
Nobody was used to that kind of story and this setting in the kitchen sink was fun and brought back the old smirking
But there wasn't much to smile at with this movie and that probably also surprised the audience.
That's very exceptional; it was for everyone.
I've never seen a cartoon this dark and gloomy again after this.
No.
You neither.
It will probably have been the last one.
The first and last one.
Oh, a Swiss ...
Well, the first will be the last.
Exactly.
Well, another funny scene, isn't it?
The movie "Der kleine Punker" still was full of those excrements, but this time we were only allowed twice, I think.
And now it gets super-theoretical.
This now is another absurdi, we can't call it absurdity. But this is very very unusual to have a cartoon beginning to theorize this ample.
All that races and genes stories and so on.
First that's unusual for cats, but even more for cartoons.
Well, yes, but er had to find a way to mediate this very complex story in a comprehemnsible and reduced way.
That'll probably be easier in a book, because I have any time in the world to explain a complex situation.
Here we just... We had to make all that comprehensible in a short timespan.
That's a difficult job with about every movie.
Yes, and it was even more difficult with this movie, because of our restricted time and the story actually requires a lot more time.
And of course we had to work atmospherical with this short timespan, because... I think the atmosphere was an essential part of this movie, so that we can mediate the story too.
So that one gets at least a feeling of what this movie is all about.
If we used weaker imagery for this movie, then we would have a relatively weakly imaginable radio play.
So we needed strong images that fit the story.
And, yes, some action once in a while, so one doesn't become bored from all those dialogs.
Naturally everything runs by the texts, it's powerfully eloquent. So is Pirincci in his book as well.
Long monologs and dialogs, overly long sentences and that kind of stuff.
That's difficult to transcript.
The movie still is crammed with text.
One probably can look it again and again and will discover something new each time.
Yes, and here you can see the teriffic computer design of that time.
Looked very strange.
This isn't a computer, this is ... dunno ...
No, but we made it look retro, it was supposed to reflect the computer design of that period.
Yes, it was something modern and futuristic...
It's hard to imagine today.
That was Arne's taste, a monitor standing upright with the boxes across.
There really were upright monitors, they were the best of the best.
Really?!
Yes.
Next Level.
It was something very special.
My first incoming feedback was: It's sitting on the wrong edge, but that's what it was supposed to be like, wasn't it?
Now something terrible has happened again, hasn't it?
Yes, another dead body announced itself.
Yes, this is the lover.
Yes.
I still remember.
We'll see a very cruel image soon.
This is the time for all children to look away. And now you can watch again - no, not yet.
Now.
Ok now, at the latest now we got the parents to turn off the movie, but...
You'd turn it off for your children?
Ah well, this might been a little too drastic now.
True.
Lately I've watched "Ants" and pulled my little daughter away, I think it's actually very brutal.
That's my philoso.. No! There is a battle where there's only a single head left over and the body is missing. And that's where I said "That wasn't necessary."
It appears brutal here, because we're near reality despite speaking cats and so on.
It's not another reality of course.
In principle, we're trying to bring in reality by the background designs, the movements of the cats, we're not trying to imitate, but we're getting near.
And then something like death appears even more real so.
Apart from that, especially cartoons are well-known for flying heads and limps. It's accepted because it is a fictive world.
Now we're getting to a scene coming from Hayo Freitag. For me this is the most creepy scene of this movie.
The "Mendel Scene" which explains a lot from the philosophie of the book.
Where we again used very complicated camera technics. Which is a discrete short film on its own by its graphic.
It was graphically complex and ambitious, too
That's such a scene which a comic artist ... craves for.
It was even under discussion when we began to develop the movie to trim the whole movie even harder, "german-expressive" than it appears from the graphic.
But then we decided on the contrast to put the story into a normal movie world and to only use this emphasively expressional forms in the dramatic scenes.
If the whole movie were made this way, then it would have been a case for the nuthouse.
Well.
It's endurable for a short dosis, but I think it wouldn't have been bearable fot the whole movie.
No no, I'm saying - we've just been discussing this.
Watching something like that for eighty minutes, that's going to be a special disclipne. I agree.
Well, wimp cat, no. That's...
Yes a stylistic device that we used throughout the movie, to never show a complete human.
And to not show heads at all
We want... The human world is a parallel world of subordinate importance in this movie.
Yes like always... Such rules are made and then I get a call from the animation crew to finally get a head for Gustav.
The face! The face is missing and they were needing it.
And then I asked back "what for?"
"Well, he's lying on the bed and then you're going to see the face and stuff."
Dann sagte ich "Ja, Moment mal. Das war doch klar vorgegeben: Keine Gesichter."
You see him up to the neck and from the back and from above and from below but never from the front.
But the scene was already that far that we had to supply a face.
Well, all rules in cartoons seem to only exist to be broken as well.
But that's also a charm of the medium.
Which scene are we seeing Gustav's face?
He lies on the bed, turns around, says something, wipes his face with his arm.
But now there's those 2, 3, 5 seconds and someone had to be bold and needed the face at all cost.
But it's funny, too.
Well, that also counts for anecdote.
I've never seen the face.
Well, here too a scene for the cat hater fraction that surely exists in the audience.
You think?
Don't think so.
Well, we have to ... well... we?
The topic here is the development of something
Quasi a kind of skin glue to close wounds.
By now I learned that it exists in reality.
Which was still a frankenstein vision in the book, long has become regular reality.
There is a glue that glues skin wounds together and works.
Progressive medicine then it is.
Probably they needed such animal experiments for it, but we don't know that.
This is another speciality of the movie, it got so many... in addition to the dreams it also has those inserts.
By switching the layers, one can split the compact story over several layers and thus arrange more interesting and more diverse.
This may be a little disgusting here, but that's also just a matter of taste.
One always should have a bottle of booze at hand when whatching this movie, so you can endure this.
Booze?
That guy just has drunk booze, the assistant, because he can't bear it anymore.
That poor guy...
Red wine!
We've kept that open.
Everybody can ... interprete what he likes.
I have to admit that we've broken our rules here again.
I've seen quite some human heads here, but not those faces, so at least we've succeeded at not showing the faces from the front or looking at the camera or taking too much importance in the image
Well, that's on television, you don't see them in real. I think that's how we excused ourselves.
Das ist aber auch...
Yeah, ok. The important point is that in principle everything has to be shown from the cats' view.
As we know, by the cats' opinion humans are just stupid can openers.
And not really important at all.
They don't show much emotions towards the humans.
The humans aren't not important in this story at all.
can opener, was it?
can opener, exactly, that's a good catchword.
Heard it 30 minutes ago, I remember.
Right, 30 minutes ago. From a cat's opinion humans aren't any good but as can openers.
After the production of this movies I denied any and every wish for pets from my family.
We didn't want that anymore by then.
I think we got us a dog then.
We some rabbit.
Well, again those animators who expended all that effort, one has too... I'd love too name them all here.
Because they finally decided to take the hard path to move the cats so smoothly and much, like they really would or should do.
It really contradicts the inertia of every animator to sit out a scene with as few drawings as possible.
But this wasn't possible at all.
It was impossible, but I think you can see it that everone enjoyed to do these experiments.
Those are those rare chances at your job where you're allowed to kick over the traces.
Where story and production allow this to happen.
Anecdote about Senator Film, the producent of this movie, they really gave us plenty of rope and also no restrictions about what's ok and not.
We have proposed those things and said "Yes, that's how it has to be, we want that." And they bravely followed us every footstep.
And here again we see one of those complex rain scenes, which had to be done with so consideribly more effort than one would do today.
Yes, there's another dead cat again, isn't there?
One has to realize that too.
Yes, the effects just add up.
So every scene with rain or bolt or fire or snow or things like that...
Splashing water!
Yes.
Those scenes are just double the work.
You can expect that.
Usually one distributes those to several places, but there's so many of them in this movie.
It starts with the shadows and it ends with the complicated elements like fire.
Or explosions.
That's what makes the movie atmospheric, like Michael said.
Well, why we all now... well, why are we so disappointed really?
Because the movie didn't run that well in the movies.
It didn't run that well that we'd say we'd do such movies again.
We had one movie of that kind and then we thought, it needed a lot of effort and the audience didn't honored it as much as we expected.
But we have to admit... we experimented with a lot of different things and we tried a lot of things that we could reuse for our later productions. "Werner", "Kleines Arschloch", "Pipi Langstrumpf", those movies benefited a lot from this know-know we gained with this movie.
But naturally there is the sad eye that says "ok, we've dont it."
We could kick over our traces.
we wanted to propagate a certain style
with much engagement. And when that doesn't work out as expected and we were spoiled by the first Werner movie with over 5 billion viewers and now Felidae had just 280, that's world between.
280.000
Yes, 280.000, We don't have to worsen our work even more ;)
No, but we have to see, it wasn't such a great success that it would have further follow-up productions.
But on the other side, we have to say that this movie helped a lot that we could do more productions in our studio here in Hamburg afterwards.
Yes, I see it as the culmination of all our options.
We really had the best people, in proven teams,
most people acted in concert for this movie and with a lot of engagement.
With a vision too, this kind of cartoon has been brand new ground for us.
And then it is a little bitter if nobody wants to watch it.
But that's an artist's question, too - do you do it for someone to watch or do you do it for joy.
That's always a litmus test.
only a producer would know the definite answer, but the creatives always seek inspiration.. so one actually seeks both.
If we do something good and if it will be watched a lot, that'd be the best result.
Fine, but that's also the difficulity in the movie business. If you knew beforehand, it'd be easy.
Then everybody would do it.
Yes, that's true.
But *when* you get the chance to make something like this, you also have to try to make the best out of it.
I think we succeeded at that with this movie.
Despite of the weakpoints that one probably notices.
I mean to say there will always be those scenes where you'd say "ok, this cat looks worse than the one over there".
That's also caused by the face that we split up the movie a lot. Between Korea, Canada and Ireland,
there's different teams on it and that's a big difficulty.
to bring those teams to a common disposition.
With each mentality there's different opinions how a cat has to move.
Of course you cannot exactly direct this from the distance when things are done.
That's the difficulty if you produce a movie in the way like we did back then.
Rather split up. But that also was the only way to produce the movie with our budget.
Else a certain improvement of the drawing quality would have been paid with three times our budget or so.
And that's just impossinble of course.
And I have to admit that it was a joy to work with many professional people that we still would not have been able to pull together at Hamburg.
One has to realize, they would not have left their home for a production which is a year of work, a year of drawing.
That would have been the deal, a big cartoon studio in Hamburg with two or three hundred involved parties.
Like Amblin in London or like in Hollywood.
But that's not imaginable in the German movie scenery.
It's all a bit too small for that.
That would have blown the scope completely.
And those people had to be kept busy after that for a while.
It wasn't a solution up to discussion.
No, it wasn't a disputable solution and I think we've found good compromises with what we produced. [HERE]
Here we got for example a scene that was animated in Asia,
and one can see that
After that it took several sudatory hours to fix those scenes somehow
But that had to be expected
By the way this is the cartoon premiere of Helge Schneider,
as Jesaya.
Who if you listen closely to the text... he is not daft.
In fact he's totally serious and this was also the beginning for more projects with Helge for other movies, too
He played even more supporting roles in "Kleines Arschloch" and "Käpt'n Blaubär"
Yes, but this was just the first contact with him and it was all great
Helge is compensating for the bad animation too
Yes, ugly animationatio-
One always has to ... with every production you have to split resources to where they're important
To get everything like perfect, yeah well, then...
There's movies trying to fulfill that entitlement, but there's also movies that ruined entires studios by this.
Yes, we wanted to work in an economic way
I think that was a good decision.
I think we have more than exhausted the chances [to edit: like doing better than possible with the resources]
I know exactly how we stumbled over the finishing line with extra day and night shift just in time
Investing more work in this movie...
But I think this movie was, just two days before premiere...
No, not like that. Like on the very last deadline where we had to finish the mixing so that we could produce the mass copies, that's when the movie was finished
And the final scenes got cut just during the mixing
Das war also so ein 'Ritt über den Bodensee', [TODO: get another metaphor, lol, I don't know this one]
but we succeeded somehow, like we did with other several other productions too.
Later we tried to have more time on the hand, because
that's wuite a nerve-wrecking situation if there's scenes to be cut just while mixing
Fixed scenes that weren't okay on the first take.
That maybe don't even fit or maybe never arrive.
That eventually arrive.
That's a totally different problem to solve.
But with this movie, I clearly remember,
have to dig in memories,
it was really ... very really tight end.
Now there's another dream sequence, where we worked extensively with foam and cload animation
'another mass scene.
Because the movie was kept relatively realistic, those scenes were the hilights for everyone.
And everything is possible with cartoons as you can see here.
They just burst, it would not have been that easy in reality.
The fantastic solutions, those probably are the more fascinating ones for all fans of animation.
Because if one tried to imitate reality with cartoon, it'd be plain wrong.
Then it would be real film in fact, that would then be richer.
By that... There's the chance with cartoon to graphically realize and extend all kinds of phantasie.
To realize those chances, that's the charm of cartoon.
That's what I like cartoons for, because one
can cross borders just like that.
And by the serious context of the movie the chances were limited
and that's why there's the split, that's why we have those breaks from normality in this movie.
Yes, exactly.
Else it'd be a little exchausting if they just talked and theorized.
That's again a... [no idea]
Exactly, that's why we anticipated those scened.
Now we even got to do a sex scene.
that's also one not so easy thing...
Do they even fuck in other movies at all? I don't know.
Can cartoon characters reproduce?
How do cartoon characters reproduce? That's the question. We had to somehow find a philosophical answer to that.
At least we got to try it one time.
As I remember this was the premiere and also the final...
of what...
Right, this scene is from Vancouver, too.
This was Steve Evangelatos, also a good old friend of the studio, who however...
used a completely different style from our Irish collegue,
Paul Bolger.
Those two didn't like each other, am I right?
At least on the drawing layer [topic? job? common work base?]
It's funny how people go out in the evening together and the very next day they argue about some drawings.
That's immament to the influffry.
Yes, of course, that's like with actors.
I want to say, the animators are our actors with all the same kinds of obsessions and allures like real actors, too. Right?
Everybody wants to excel best.
We don't, do we?
No, we don't care about those things.
From time to time I can sound Mario Adorf out.
I really remember that cooperation, it was not pretentious at all.
That's some Francis... I think those are the first scenes of this movie.
You don't just begin with the first scenes, but where you know that you can just start.
Here he still looks different from the other parts of the movie.
We can admit that now ... after eight year.
True, we can admit that today.
One hopes that nobody notices, but you cannot just...
The characters continuously developed. I think Francis had six different shapes in the beginning.
In the end nobody knew the exact difference and we said, it's ok because the animators already started to move his body.
And there's a limit to changes somewhere.
Later he looks a little rounder, here he still has some sharp edges.
But you cannot redo a scene that just works, you cannot redo that three times.
And we ... just didn't have the resources for that.
But I don't see any point in ...
It's the premiere for you to reveral that fact. Else nobody would have noticed it.
No, exactly. May I even revel that?
No, now you just have, now it's too late, but...
and as I said...
Now we let out the cat, which we didn't want to really.
Now we let out the cat, about all that we did wrong.
Now then, say something good again.
The sky is nice, yes.
Yes, there's moving clouds on the sky at times, which aren't as nice anymore.
It was difficult, to express the threatening atmosphere,  especially in the clouds.
Because even a Vermeer or similar, that one trys to perform on the panorama...
Now he's gone mad.
Now look.
That's Desmond Downes, who made the art direction of the movie,
who did an excellent job.
And he still was to despair because you always can do better.
Where is Desmond now at?
He is at Dreamworks, he is at Dreamworks.
Armen is at Dreamworks, too
Steve still is in Vancouver; has his own studio.
Paul..
returned to Irland, but works with music now or something.
Yes.
The collegues who helped working on this movie, they got scattered all over the place over time.
They were bevore and concentrated on this task and some of them stayed longer with us
But you cannot expect those wandering drawes to settle in Hamburg for the rest of their life.
A gipsy movie if you call it like that.
The most exhausting recordings where those with Brandauer.
That was... I have to say I was happy when that was over.
That was a little too capricious.
But one can hear that. It really sounds nice, right?
Caprious, I said.
I'm not talking of the result, but of the way we did the recordings.
In contrary to Mario Adorf, where everything fit and if one wanted to correct a recording, then he always cooperated.
That was very professional.
Ulrich Tukur had to do his recordings five times.
That got much more time consuming than we imagined,
because he just wanted to continue his theatre character.
That doesn't work out that nice, but in the end we tortured him until finally succeeded.
Yes, the recordings are an important part of the movie production.
My wife Angelika directed the recording.
She now does some things on her own.
And back then she handled all that stuff.
And she had to really suffer with Brandauer, who didn't like being corrected at all.
And that was very difficult to handle.
But then again that was a new interesting experience.
To be in company with that squad of expensive and good actors.
Those recordings usually are done withing few days with full concentration.
That's now a task to spend weeks on, but I think we spend one week in Munich to do all of the recordings.
Yes, there's a rule of thumb:
If you do more than few takes, #1, #2, #3... it's only getting worse.
Yes.
With Ulrich Tukur we had to repeat for hours some some parts.
Because his recordings sounded emotionless.
He may excuse us if he hears us, but I think we will agree.
It wasn't so easy.
But of course, Ulrich Tukur's character is the mos ungrateful for a speaker.
the hero role.
The heros always are the boring ones.
Yes, that's maybe why... That's something we had to fight for Francis to always be the know-it-all.
It's like... undoubtly he guides us through the movie.
He's in nearly all scenes, at least in every sequence.
And yes, after a while he got on our, at least a little on my nerves.
Because, well, he can do everything, knows everything, does everything...
Just plain boring.
Francis super hero, yes.
Francis super hero just is boring.
Just unlike Blaubart or Jesaja, that how it is.
Those broken... crazy characters, those are just great.
...characters
That's something one can work with.
But the difficulties really lie with the main characters, the heros, the good guys.
That's why every Disney movie has a strong counterpart.
Any super bad guys, that are bad and...
Those are probably the favorites with the animators and creatives.
Yes, the good guys always have a companion so they don't appear as unsymphatic.
Yes, like it's with this movie...
Here comes Blaubart.
Here's Blaubart, yes.
Yes, Mickey is accompanied by Goofy.
You can always send along a companion to prevent the worst,
when always the good guy wins.
No, by that we have solved, not us, but the author Akif Prinçci, he's solved it the classic way.
We were grateful for that, because Blaubart prevented the worst.
If we were left with just Francis, then a there was a lot less emotion and fun involved.
Oh, one of the mass scenes.
Yes, they wag a little around now.
But they're not important, we only care for the talking ones.
That's where one had to watch how to spend ones money, am I right? and the time.
Pan out!
It's funny, now that there's this dramatic quarrel.
That probably was 60-80%, I dunno, three quarter foreign employees we had.
They have found something uniquely German in this story
and made a little cult out of it,
to tease us especially hard with German words.
But it was a Turkish author.
Well...
I don't attach too much to it,
but that, the genetic topic that's important,
as like as the race breeding and...
the very serious and intellectual recitation of language,
that was something significant to "German". But
I've always tried to...
we always tried to ignore it.
Yes, we're really not like that.
Yes, we always could back down to the Turkish author and say "That can't be."
"It's not a German author."
Finally a cute cat.
This was the only scene for kids here.
such an imported cat.
Pepeline was her name I think, has a cute nickname too.
Much explanation of the story works by the dialogue.
That certainly makes it a little difficult.
Not so much like we're trying to maneuver around critic,
it's just, we...
the big difficulty with this movie is ... it's very heavy on the text.
Yes, the story just is too complex.
That's the story, yes.
The story is complex and don't extend much in to praxis and reality,
but focused on all that hidden world of theories
and that has to be somehow complex or it'd be be easy to see through since the beginning.
In fact this just is like a historical detective story plot.
And we tried hard.
It isn't not near our speciality.
That was unique.
I've never experienced again for a story to be so focused on itself.
And the movie has to do all the preliminary work.
Others...
Because it'd not work in any other way,...
Well, yes.
It's based on the novel.
It's succesful, we cannot just...
No really, but it was quite a hard change from "Der kleine Punker", wasn't it?
That was quite the change, yes.
[gibberish]
I also believe that the "Ottifanten", the way it was shown on television, there was no joke too bad to skip it.
Yes, now we concentrated on the artwork,
on the animation on the coating with music and
sounds.
Within the limits of our possibilities and
really, one has to emphasiz our possibilities that...
were about a sixth or seventh of what, or a eithth[??] of what's common in America.
Hum we had... considerably less.
I think about a tenth.
Well, ok a tenth then.
For the same amount of minutes.
Actually we should only show a tenth, maybe a tenth of the picture or something.
No, I wouldn't over do it like that.
We all had our fun at it.
We succeeded in completing it within the limits of our possi--
That's Mongo!
Well, in the pictures you can see to persons from the staff, they've left their mark.
There's another one.
This is Mendel again.
But those small gags, they sneak in over and over.
There's people that seem to study that kind of stuff.
Mistakes and Bonmots hidden in cartoons.
I didn't intend to point out all mistakes here.
Or else we'd talk ourselves down.
That's not a mistake, it's an enrichment.
No,, those are little gags, I perceive them as an enrichment.
No, we won't pick at the mistakes. We won't talk about them.
No, we'll conceil them decently.
We've pointed out some of them now, that's got to be enough.
The addicted audience may now, may make their own opinion.
In the end, if he now watches the dvd then
no he has it alredy, hasn't he.
Yes.
Then he could look for more mistakes.
Right.
Now we're getting towards the resolution of the story.
The Showdown.
I'm looking forward to it, it's especially extensive on effects, because
we also had to animate fire.
Again...
Had to animate slow motion.
So we were allowed to play for a minute by including flashbacks,
to finally explain the story, because that's really necessary.
Or else, really, or else you cannot understand it.
One has to add the continuation novel,
there was a second felidae novel,
it wasn't
not as successful like this first book.
I believe this book it was an exceptionelly successful novell.
That was another moment, when we...
That was another cat specific animation.
Right, in the sense of a cartoon company.
Okay, with todays technic...
Sometimes on the surface of the movie...e des Filmes so
you can see scratches or fluff.
This won't happen anymore.
This doesn't exist anymore, because that kind of stuff happens because of using cameras.
That's just little pieces of fluff on the film.
And the film also charge statically,
and attract that fluff by that.
And you can see it especially well with dark backgrounds.
This movie consists to ninety percent of dark backgrounds, so
we technically always were at risk.
And given that, I have to say, you don't see very much of it.
There's some scenes which look very dirty.
I didn't point out those.
But it really looks relatively fine.
That was an additional problem with the takes.
We had to keep things extremely clean.
Yes, well...
For old-fashioned movie connaiseurs those small things are all charming.
But they will be gone in the era of computers.
No, because the basic techniques,
like how the camera takes are composed,
changed massively.
Everything is going to be done digitally, there's no fluff anymore.
That's fluff free movies for a fluff free world.
Yes, exactly.
Around 1998 we also
we also passed over to not using cameras anymore.
Now, we fork only with computers since 3 years ago.
and we have, the camera we've used also with this movie
and the one before, we bought them both from Richard Williams,
this one has also been used to produce "Roger Rabbit",
this camera now resides in out conference room as a
museum piece; only has scrap value today.
I think that it was originally expensive as half a billion.
we bought it back then already for much less
and by now it only has enthusiast value.
That's in ones mind a huge change,
to move from the mechanical and manual love
to the digital world.
And that's a huge challenge for the drawers, and the painters and for the actual camera people
a huge challenge to not lose that
charming quality,
when you're suddenly only starring on a computer surface,
and then hack around on some keys.
Of course you'll glide more smoothely with a pencil and of course
you'll move a little more careful with the camera desk,
than when you bend some vectors.
I've enjoyed working with cameras, with that mechanic stuff, very much...
but...
I also have to agree with the result, the problems we had with the film and also
when one winded up the wrong direction or the camera ...
the camera ride [term!] didn't turn out as expected,
One had to repeat a lot of work again and again.
Then from the point of effort,...
In the end the audience cares for the result,
... which sticks.
And now we see the show down.
fire and action and
then we have put another hilight here towards the end,
where we could give some candy for our animators again.
Yes, our fx animators could run riot here again once more.
At this scene I recall those
plain naked sound recordins with Mister Brandauer who was supposed to emit
fighting noise without seeing any picture.
You've got to imagine this without music and all that, it sounded quite strange.
Demonstrate it.
No, I won't.
I did... I leave that to only and just only to Mister Brandauer
and the imagination of our audience here.
Just imagine the noise and music turned off, what's left then?
Meooow~  [This line was what I was given my the person who provided with me with the script]
Yes.
Yes, animated slow motion.
Yes, that's the Rob Koo at his best,
a Chi...Japanese Canadian, or China,
I don't want to do unjust.
Chinese!
He has done the storyboard for half of the movie,
A pillar of the movie story with the cut sequence [movie term I'm not familiar with]
A brilliant professional and he helped us a lot.
Well, the asian heritage, there's a little...
It shows a little with the style if you compare this with todays manga movies [I'd prefer to call it anime because that's the correct term, but they really say it like that :/]
You can't deny the parallels.
As in camera positioning and...
it is like that with this Rob Koo,
who then worked with Armen Melkonian in Canada,
he got influenced a lot.
We've been pioneers with this again somehow.
Now the show down, now we were allowed to break anything that we were capabable to.
Another dream.
Blood.
My god, and then the movie is already over.
No, now there's still an epilog.
To color everything in nice colors, to say "everything's ok, life goes on" and stuff...
This had to happen.
We don't want our audience to collapse now, do we.
No, we want to stay a little on the optimistic side.
Yes, now we induce a cool athmosphere and then nothing at all.
They're spoiled anyway, they always want a happy end and now it arrived.
That's how it's supposed to be!
No, we couldn't have made it end like that,
now I have to disgree.
We have to finish this positively.
Back then we have wished to maybe do a second movie, but
it wasn't confirmed then.
No, we're born optomists.
Exactly, but it didn't work out that time.
It didn't work out that time.
But then we were allowed to produce "Werner" and "Kleines Arschloch".
... quit it now.
Okay.
Fine.
So, good bye.
Dear audience, it's over.
I hope,
you enjoyed what we we could tell you about the movie.
Thank you.
Yes, I say good-bye as well.
Good bye!